hello and welcome everyone it's
September 30th 2023 and we are in
physics as information processing
discussion 5 should be a fun discussion
on a great fifth lecture
so
Andre if you'd like to give some opening
remarks
and then also anyone else whether it's
your first time joining a discussion or
not it would be great to hear your
remarks on lecture five or just where
you're coming at it today so first
though Entre
sure hello Daniel
um so
I may as well start off by sharing the
slides right what do you think
sure
uh so just just uh before that's a
warm-up
um let's let's review some of the things
that Chris mentioned last time
so
um
near the beginning the main thing was
this distinction between reductionist
and scale free theories
um
obviously one one very Salient feature
of of
um the free energy literature is that uh
it falls under scale free theories these
are theories where there is no
preferred scale of energy or distance
um
reduction its uh theories are based on
on such a scale existence right you you
want to break
the pieces into the fundamental building
blocks of the Legos you know people
think of usually high energy or particle
physics as they you as the archetype of
this thing
um
whereas in is in scale three theories uh
there is no such thing and and we should
we should have the same
skeletons or the same framework
um at different scales
um this is going to be very important I
I Chris correct me if I'm wrong but
especially for the coming lecture where
we talk about biology Chris himself made
a few remarks on how the renormalization
group flow
aka the process of going from from
smaller to higher scale maybe trivial in
biology that is to say that um there is
a self-similarity okay so so some
features of biology should remain
invariant at different scales that is
um what cells are to a body different
individuals
of a species might be to a to an
ecosystem that that sort of idea
um So after talking out scale
and and perhaps
um
when we get to the question part I guess
this is the one thing that I like uh
Chris to explain a little more uh more
precisely what these diagrams mean I
have a rough idea but it would it would
be nice to hear him talk about that
again uh anyways
in the second half basically
um we started asking as is the theme in
in this in this in this course so far
from first principles
what do you need to talk about
um space space on time and
um there were some theorizing that time
might be
um more fundamental that is the things
that you need for to implement the clock
we're thinking about what are the most
basic constituents to implement a clock
and those may be even more basic than
the things you need to implement qrfs or
perception of space after all
it seems like you need some spatial
extension to perceive a space in the
first place I can't remember if it was
somebody who was tuning in for the
lecture or a question afterwards or
something like that
but I I think this this remark gets to a
very deep point
somebody I recall mentioned
that some organisms it might have
increased himself I can't remember
really that there are organisms you may
know the name Daniel that are so tiny
that if they if they try to implement a
gradient
to try to chase you know their food or
whatever they're they're so small that
they can't even perceive the gradient
you know like in any any attempt at
implementing such perception
they're gonna feel
uh they're gonna feel the same amount of
concentration in all directions so
they're basically not large enough to
perceive space however
uh interestingly so they can they can
perceive time I don't know how this ties
to the remarks
that Chris made about space being more
fundamental I suppose
Chris was getting at the point that you
need fewer parts to perceive space and
the the fact that such small organisms
um compressive time but not space I
guess is further empirical evidence for
this thesis
and um
I actually Andrew if I can uh
yeah I I proposed earlier that that time
is actually more fundamental in space
that one has to have time
uh to be able to see space so that's
further on in these slides uh that issue
is discussed yeah so did I do you want
to say something about deckers
well this is the right slide that
um
yeah one
one just needs a memory really to
uh to have a clock an ex an external
clock I mean to get to have an internal
clock when just when
one also has to have a memory do I have
an internal clock but if you have a
memory
and there's some kind of uh activity
that's
uh periodic in the environment then you
have a clock
an external clock
uh but you don't need object identity to
have a clock
and that's how what distinguishes it
from space you have to have object of
identity
uh or in other words motion the ability
to perceive motion to perceive space
right
yeah any periodic behavior is
effectively a clock whereas
you know for space we need um
object persistence which uh two comments
that we've made where that
object persistence is the or rather
Chris made uh is the defining feature of
classicality you said that last time is
that right Chris and also that object
persistence is
is precisely the notion of thickness uh
the way Christian would put it
yeah yeah object persistence is is
definitely a classical notion
and it it does seem to be the the place
where classicality enters quantum theory
as far as I can tell is is with this
notion of object persistence that that's
the most fundamental place that it
enters
so so how does that definition of or
rather relationship between classicality
and quantumness
um
be an object object persistence how does
it compare with other accounts coming
from
from qdar and the coherence and all of
that
um
well say Quantum Darwinism is is a good
example uh Quantum Darwinism assumes
object persistence right it assumes that
there is some
persistent thing that interacts over
time with the environment
uh According to some interaction that
has fixed eigenvalues
so uh
Quantum Darwinism already assumes object
persistence
and it also assumes classical
communication as we discussed a couple
of times ago in that it's
a theory
that is about the ability of multiple
observers to agree about
the state of some
some other object
which for them to agree about it that
object not only does the object need to
persist the the various observers need
to have the same description of that
object
or the same name for that object or or
the same way of identifying that object
so yeah Quantum organism actually
assumes a lot of classical features
uh the basic theory of Environmental
decoherence
is
in effect a single Observer Theory
so it doesn't have to assume classical
communication but it does assume object
persistence
which
which obviously you forget to talk about
empirical science you have to right you
have to assume that your detector is a
thing that persists through time or you
can't do an experiment and more
importantly than that you have to assume
that you're a thing that persists
Through Time
so
so we need these classical Notions to
talk about doing science
yeah I'm not the first person to point
that out of course I mean boar pointed
that out in 1928 in this paper in
science where he summarizes
quantum theory
so it's a very very old idea
right
and I guess
um right away I have a question that I
suspect I may have asked before but
maybe we can revisit it with um
from the perspective of today's
discussion which is and maybe I should
pull
uh the slide this is actually from
session four
um so if we're talking about
differences between
um
what what the defining feature of
classicality is uh to me that bears the
question of
here right this tqft
um diagrammatic notation for
the the classical and the quantum
channels so so if we're talking about
object persistence as the defining
feature of classicality and this is the
cartoon picture of what goes on on epr
experiment uh Chris could you say maybe
a few words
about how
that classical like how how the Symmetry
is broken between the quantum and
classical channels I
suspect it might have been mentioned
that these are symmetrical but yet one
of the two has to be a Quantum and the
other one is a classical channel the
quantum Channel
um
mediates some sort of unitary evolution
is that correct whereas the classical
channel is is like an information
redundant redundancy Reservoir
um
which which maybe has to do something
with class with object persistence but I
I very much speculating at this point so
I'm not sure if Chrissy have any
comments
yeah well an easy way to think about
this I think is to to actually think
about a bell epr experiment where you
have two
observers that are separated in space so
so you know we you have to assume here
the to talk about Bell APR you have to
assume the notion of space
to have a laboratory reference frame
uh in which the two observers are are
spatially separated
and in that situation
then uh the two observers both
independently collect data for some
amount of time
on on multiple replicas of some Quantum
state
um that's produced by a source so you
have pairs of photons or pairs of
electrons or pairs of whatever
and
at some point the data collection stops
and at that point The Observers have to
compare their results
so it's the it's the comparison step
that requires a classical Channel
and uh
if you if you think about how this
happens in practice
how it happens via uh
a file sent over the Internet or
a
[Music]
piece of paper on which the data are
written that's handed by one of the
experimenters to the other experimenter
or it happens by the experimenters
talking to each other so so one
experimenter encodes a bunch of a bunch
of information in in the ambient air
and the other experimenter hears it
uh or it could be communicated by light
signals right but it's always
communicated by some medium
and uh that's what defines
classical communication it's
communication via a medium
that persists through time in the
observer's reference frame
um
and
the
the minimum time of the Persistence of
that Medium is given by the speed of
light
so if The Observers are a foot apart and
they're communicating by a light signal
then it may only last in nanosecond
oh but if they're talking to each other
you know it lasts several seconds
and if they're if they exchange a piece
of paper and then that piece of paper
May last for years
in a lab notebook someplace
so uh
there's always the question of
persistence over time
that is
deeply bound up with this notion of
classicality
as a process that takes time
information has to flow has to be
encoded in a medium and then read from
that Medium
in some finite amount of time
and
in a sense we're assuming something like
that in the quantum description
when we think of this boundary
via which the
A and B
the the physical components interact
oh
if we think of that boundary as a qubit
array then each of those qubits persists
Through Time
and that's what allows them to
encode classical information so encode
observational outcomes that are repeated
in time
that's what allows them to serve as a
memory to
to
encode information in a way that's
thermodynamically irreversible
and if you think of the boundary in that
way as the qubit array then it has a
certain thickness in time
it's it's it's two plank times thick
right the plank time is 10 to the minus
43 seconds so it's it's
unmeasurably small
but the operation of interacting with
the qubit
uh
is a physical interaction
that uh
relativistic point of view has to take
this minimal time
so we're
it's it's in a sense
time persistence for times that are
significantly longer than the plank time
that is the marker of classicality here
but but even these plank time
even even persistence over the plank
time
um
is a necessary ingredient for talking
about communication even even Quantum
communication
so it's a very very deep concept
with a with a very long philosophical
history going back to you know the ship
of Theseus and all that people have been
wondering about what does it mean to say
that something persists Through Time
just
anyone want to make a comment on that or
bring in a new question
please feel free to if you haven't
brought up anything yet
um sure I can I can speak more I mean um
if you don't mind
uh I also recall uh and Chris correct me
if I'm wrong
we we said that
related to what you just said
that uh clock tick is always tantamount
to one of this
um classical channels is that is that
correct did I remember that correctly
Chris
yeah
uh an internal clock corresponds to
an irreversible right on the boundary
um so one can then ask what does it mean
to say that that's irreversible
um
what it means is it took some energy to
do it
and
if you go back to to read that bit again
there's at least a reasonably high
probability that it's still
is in the same state that you wrote it
in right and clearly that probability is
going to degrade through time because
the
that action is on the boundary so
whatever you've written whatever bits
that you've written are now exposed to
the environment so if Alice writes that
they're now exposed to Bob and to Bob's
Dynamics
so
um
as As Time Goes On by your internal
clock or any external clock the
probability of that memory being the
same when you go back to read it slowly
decreases or maybe it decreases fast
and you know we know that from our own
case our own memories degrade Through
Time
uh because the physical world is
interacting with our brains in ways that
we don't control
and
uh
you know
killing neurons are changing their
activity or whatever
so whenever we talk about memory
uh it's always with this caveat that
the the memory is exposed to the
environment and it's not guaranteed to
be the same
it's it's only kind of
um
a great grace of the environment being
reasonably benign
that any of us have memories at all
and and so um so this thermodynamic cost
to
to to classical information sharing or
or writing
um this in a sense would it be fair to
say that in a sense the price you have
to pay to to protect against the
coherence or you know and entangling
this sector with a with the rest of the
environment
um just to preserve its its identity
would that be fair to say
oh yeah I mean you can think of
decoherence as a good thing or you can
think of decoherence as a bad thing
right if you're if you're trying to
preserve a Quantum State then it's a bad
thing you have to spend energy to
prevent decoherence by you know
cooling everything down to millikelvins
oh but if you're interested in
preserving classical data then
decoherence is a good thing because it
prevents your classical data from being
completely rearranged by becoming
entangled with the environment
so I mean think about trying to to write
classical memories in using the states
of atoms
in the middle of the sun and the
temperatures so high that uh
you can't do anything you can't
rearrange the atoms in any way and
expect them to stay put
so
there you're in effectively a completely
Quantum environment
just because of the high temperature so
it's it's a plasma
yeah and then just one one final
question that popped to my mind as you
say this and I can certainly leave it
here for everyone else
um
so if we're trying to protect about
against the random
um lawsuits against the loss of
information
uh I suppose
it really backs the question of um what
is the source of this noise that can
perturb the bits in the binary
um with there's there's obviously this
this distinction between a thermal and
Quantum noise you know again it's a
stretch to see if we can think back
about the weak rotation about that but
um again I recall earlier sessions where
we talk how the noise here in this
Quantum theoretic picture of information
uh processing is coming from the QRS
failing to be aligned
um then you know
you hear about Notions of quantum noise
versus thermal noise uh Chris do you
have any comments on all of that
um yeah
I think an important thing here
let me back up
yeah the notion of noise like so many
other Notions
is
very often
uh treated as objective as Observer
independent
and so when we're doing classical
physics we think of noise as just you
know there's there's some objective
Randomness in the universe and we call
that noise
so in this picture because we're working
with just a bipartite decomposition
right we just have Alice and Bob and
that's it that's the entire universe
um there's there's no external
environment here to impose any sort of
noise
but since we only have two systems
of Alice and Bob equals everything else
you know not Alice
then uh
if we talk about Bob being a noisy
environment that's clearly relative to
this boundary we've drawn between Alice
and Bob so so noise isn't Observer
independent what's what's noise for
Alice is just Bob's Dynamics
right so
so uh
if if you think about where these
systems come from you've got some
universe
that
um
is in some
pure State because it's an isolated
system
and uh
that state is
evolving through time which means it's
just undergoing phase rotation
so there's no noise in that system
right it's perfectly unitary etc etc as
soon as you draw a boundary
then
there's information that the system on
one side of the boundary doesn't have
about the system on the other side
so uh
the individual systems
are
uh
their states can now be considered
conditionally independent I mean you can
you can come up with a description in
which their states are conditionally
independent
and that just means
that what the other side is doing
uh looks like noise
unless uh Alice say
can come up with a way of analyzing the
data that she sees on her boundary
uh in a way that makes it make sense
right and then it's then it's then it's
do we say it's information for Alice but
what does that mean it just means it's
behavior on her boundary that she's
smart enough to assign some kind of
semantics to
um
and if she's not smart enough to do that
then it's just noise
so as soon as you make the decision you
make the notion of noise Observer
dependent it it turns into something
that makes a lot more sense
mm-hmm
and and just to really finish this uh
I guess it's been it's been a couple
months at least but I think it was back
in July that we
we talked about
um
the distinction between what you're
saying which is uh things having the
appearance of noise just because you
you have finite resources so you cannot
make sense of Bob's internal Dynamics
as opposed to
um in one of in that cartoon of the of
the four possibilities for qrf
alignments right some of them were uh
thermal in the sense that one one side
was was acting on a on a boundary acute
while the other one was none so the then
it truly looks like
like noise to the other side
um does that does that get to the bottom
of the distinction between Quantum and
thermal noise at all Chris or am I
misunderstanding things here yeah it
yeah it turns the distinction into
essentially a relative
a
qrf relative distinction
right right if if
uh you know
I mean languages provide a good example
I mean think of going to some place
where you don't understand the language
at all like you know Papua New Guinea or
something like that
I certainly wouldn't understand the
language
oh
that that language
the behavior is speaking that language
encodes lots of information for those
people and it codes no information at
all for me
so it looks like noise to me I can't
make sense of it
but it's not always from their point of
view
um
and
now let's think about this need to have
a thermodynamic sector if you're a an
organism
that has to burn energy or any system
that has to burn energy to
to to
act irreversibly on your environment
of that thermodynamic sector looks to
you like noise but it's it's just
temperature Heat
and uh you use that heat to drive your
processing and if you're a really good
heat engine
then you can use it pretty efficiently
and get you know a lot of bang for the
buck in terms of information processing
if you're really inefficient heat engine
then
um
maybe it you have to use almost your
entire environment as heat to do any
little bit of information processing at
all
so that's not a statement about the
universe as a whole that's the statement
about you and and your information
processing capabilities in your in your
thermal
your heat processing capabilities you
know how how good is your Carnot cycle
right
determines how the amount of information
processing it can do
thank you Chris um Ian
hi uh yeah thank you everyone for
putting on this series it's the first
time I've joined the discussion sessions
and
um
yeah so it's a question about in one of
the slides there was
um a green rectangle
and we were talking about that being a
or Chris was talking about that being a
kind of
um thinking of that as a
bacterium
um and it got me
wondering whether
like how how else I could get an
intuitive grasp of this kind of
space-time emerging
um
and
so what I was thinking is you know it
appears like to us humans it appears
like the universe is
expanding
um through time and I was just trying to
think you know a bacterium if we placed
a single bacterium on a petri dish
um at Time Zero
and or even something more simple you
know let's say deep sea hydrothermal
vent where life was supposed to are you
know these agents were supposed to have
maybe begun existing as
um phospholipid type molecules so I was
just wondering
you know if I was if I was a
phospholipid within that bacterial
membrane
um just a single one single phospholipid
and all I can measure is the existence
of
phospholipidus or not phospholipidus
um
or and selfness and not selfness then
you know I was just trying to imagine as
this bacteria divides after 20 minutes
let's say the average sort of bacterial
division time then before that happened
all I could tell was I'm surrounded by
phospholipinus so there was no real
distinction
in my environment but once
um the bacteria is divided into two then
I'm sitting then I'm observing some
phospholipinus which isn't in my
sort of
what I call my own boundary
um so then I've kind of created space
space and time is starting to appear
even though the petri dish hasn't
changed in size
or my you know the universe hasn't
really changed
but it's the
um
phospholipids the orientation of the
phospholipids so yeah I kind of I was
just trying to liken it if this is a
scale
invariant principle how can we liken it
to how other
things might experience space and time
emerging that's where I was coming from
am I kind of totally barking up the
wrong tree with that or is there is that
no I I think that's I think that's a
really good question and I I think
you're you're constructing
a very good kind of thought experiment
and it's it's this sort of question that
I'm really going to try to address in
October
of
how how can we think about
the fep is a scale fury theory
uh
in practice you know as as applying at
the level of of macromolecules as you
were just describing you know how do we
come up with a description of what a
phospholipid say can actually measure uh
what actually affects its state
and uh you know to what extent does it
have a self-representation
oh
my guess is that a phospholipid probably
doesn't
but a bacterium seems to have at least
some degree of self-representation I
mean it has
um
an immune system it can feel stress
so it's starting to seem like
uh an organism that's not that different
from us
oh
but
even even something like E coli
it can certain it certainly behaves in
what we call space
but it's at least not clear to me that
it has a representation of space
oh
[Music]
although it it
their processes in the E coli that do
distinguish
say
of the two ends of the E coli I mean
even if you think of the chemotaxis
pathway
uh the two ends of that pathway are
quite distinct functionally
so perhaps E coli has a one-dimensional
representation of space it can tell it's
anterior end from its posteriorate
but perhaps it doesn't have
any representation of what we would call
left and right or up and down
so
um
but if you look at multicellular
organisms
of
even something like say Hydro
how
is
especially quite sophisticated kind of
thing I mean it's not bilateral
it's cylindrically symmetrical
oh
but
it's got a very large distinction
between anterior and posterior and it
seems to know quite a bit
at least I understand from people who
work on Hydra about
um its own body the state of its own
body
and
so I think these are are exactly the
same kinds of questions that we should
be asking and they also apply at the
scale that's much larger than us so if
we think about
a human society for example as an agent
what can that agent measure and what can
that agent represent
and
uh
how complex can that agent's cognition
be
and I
think those questions are all
essentially open
so yeah it's a great thought experiment
I think it addresses exactly the
questions that we're interested in
addressing here
thank you Chris Harris and then anyone
else with a raised hands
yes uh thank you once again for allowing
me to be here with all of you
uh interesting as always
so I have a question that is related to
this notion of of the dual aspect of
information basically
that
the meaning of formation is not just a
matter of interpretation
but rather it is rudely in rooted in the
physical properties of the system under
investigation
so basically that as I understand it
means translates that the meaning of
information is not separate from the
physical properties of the system under
investigation
um but it is rather an intrinsic part of
it
so uh I I am also familiar
um with this uh notion of uh from from
the theory of computation called then
Bremer response limit that is a limit on
the maximum rate of computation that can
be achieved let's say in a self-cost
contained system uh within the material
universe
so my question is how can we
parse let's say
though that that sort of uh
computational limit in terms of
information processing
thank you
I am not sure
that we can talk about a
I think it's very difficult to talk
about
the the
classical information processing
capability of the universe as a whole
how
I mean one has to impose some sort of
classical description
and the question is then where does that
description come from and
uh from from kind of whose point of view
is that a description
but certainly as soon as we you
partition the universe as a whole into
some some system and some other system
uh
one can immediately talk about
their information processing
capabilities
and
then the question Becomes of
Quantum information processing
capabilities versus classical
information processing capabilities
and
um
if you're if you're looking at classical
information processing
to the extent that it's not reversible
um
it requires energy
and so one can immediately derive limits
based on the free energy access of that
system
if you're talking about reversible
information processing which which
purely Quantum information processing is
then you don't have that energetic
requirement
but you also don't have a well-defined
answer right in any classical terms
and it's
it's only the if if Alice is your system
of Interest
that's able to do Quantum information
processing
then it's only her interaction partner
Bob
who can can use her as a quantum
computer
and then uh his ability to
uh
employ Alice as a quantum computer
is limited by his classical information
processing capabilities because he has
to define a classical input and a
classical output
I'll
so
I think this question becomes very
complicated as
as soon as it is cast in these
Observer relative terms
yeah but but but such limits clearly
exist
right they they just require certain
assumptions to Define them
so Quantum information
and indeed we understood us a kind of
dual to the classical information right
um
yes
and it's
it's essentially one of these bulk
boundary type dualities that that seem
now to be ubiquitous in physics
if we think of
um I'm just thinking in terms of the
holographic principle
um you can have Quantum processing going
on in in the bulk in in the system that
has a boundary
and that can encode it can that can read
classical information from the boundary
and encode classical information on the
boundary
and
the
quantitatively the holographic principle
tells you how much right what can the
maximum entropy classical entropy of the
boundary be
um
but
what it doesn't tell you is anything
about the semantics that
either the system inside assigns to the
information or any Observer outside
assigns to the information
it just it's just a quantitative
statement
so in in any setting that that's
characterized by that principle
[Music]
um
the classical information on the
boundary is is dual in an interesting
sense too the quantum processing that's
going on
inside
uh in that it
that classical information on the
boundary encodes
everything that an external Observer can
know about what's going on on the inside
thank you yes now
okay yeah
on it and then Dean after
bye thank you very much
um I'm also new to
um your active inference and your course
uh I just want to say that unfortunately
I work with humans and uh
um but and I say unfortunately because
uh the complexities are horrific
um
so
uh having said that maybe my my question
will make sense
um so as I'm learning about
Quantum information Theory
and I'm what I'm trying to do is assess
how can this help me answer questions
that I have in the systems that I work
with
my question is
in order to have
a
time Arrow
irreversible process
don't you need to have a goal
and so answer my question is does it
matter to even worry about goals
because
as I listen to all the descriptions and
I think about Alice and Bob and systems
I immediately think about well
so much of what we're talking about
depends upon the goal of the system
and in some very abstract way
it seems to me that there is a goal
that's driving
the need for the boundary the need for
the communication
um and so
um I'm I I'm so obsessed with this
question that I wanted to ask about ask
it early on before I proceed with my
learning
uh yeah that's that's a very good
question I'm
you can think of the whole free energy
principle
as a
a way of of
describing physical systems
in a way that makes their behavior as
agents uh obvious
and so the the Effie you could State the
fep by saying that
every system has a gulf
and its goal is minimizing prediction
error
right admit it or
to put it positively
its goal is to
predict and therefore respond to
its environments actions
in a way that preserves its own identity
and
I don't know whether you've read much of
Carl fritzen's work but he uses the word
self-evidencing a lot
it says the goal of any system is to
uh generate evidence of its own
existence
which sounds very psychological and
Carl interestingly enough
studied first as a psychiatrist
so I expect that his point of view is
actually very constant with uh your
question and where you're coming from
here
um yeah actually I I started oh I'm
sorry I didn't need to interrupt
no no go ahead uh no I I started I've
spent some time reading
um
Chris feisen's
um ideas and work on
um
oh the free energy principle and uh
self-evidencing and yes I will continue
to dig deep
uh the problem is so I'm an
anthropologist and I've worked with
um
indigenous peoples and spent 20 years of
my life living in these small-scale
societies
um
and and so one of my observations is
that and that that I find really
fascinating
um
but we don't have a good understanding
of it and that's why I decided to dig
into
physics as information processing uh
which is that goals are constantly being
negotiated
and it's it's uh in more along the lines
uh so Michael Levine's work has actually
was what led me to explore Quantum
information
Theory
um
which is you know like this Collective
intelligences that are exists within
systems
and so at each level of collective
intelligence
it's not just that you have a collective
dictating a goal but that those goals
are being negotiated uh with as
different as the environments change and
as relationships between the systems
change so I know these These are uh very
big questions but if you could just like
help me
uh
give me some thoughts on what your
thoughts have been about these kinds of
questions
um yeah I think you're pointing to
something very important here and uh
uh this is uh
a question that
um
this kind of
free energy principle based work
motivates immediately
uh when you consider A system that
comprises a bunch of of subsystems
um
you know I I work with Mike Michael
Levin at Tufts in developmental biology
yeah and one of his
um
slogans as all intelligence as
collective
and that immediately
brings up this issue of of how do these
components as you put it uh
negotiate their goals how do they how do
they uh collaborate how do they compete
to what extent are they trying to
deceive each other or coerce each other
or all of us
and we're you know trying to apply this
in a Cell Biology context
as a as a description of development and
morphogenesis I mean if you think about
cells in a developing organism
they're constantly facing new
environments
uh their capabilities are constantly
changing
and how they interact with each other is
constantly changing
and this all seems very psychological or
sociological
so I I think what you're pointing to is
the ubiquitous need for this kind of
language
um
in areas other than the human Sciences I
mean it's language that's developed
within the human Sciences
it is language that seems to be
important
um
at at much smaller scales
and you know clearly when I what would
anticipate it being important in much
larger scales you know the scales of
countries are civilizations or whatever
so
um
I guess my answer is yes this is an
extremely important point of view
with very broad implications for how we
think about biology at least
thank you
definitely looking forward to your
continued learnings and journey
thank you so much
Dean
yeah my question has changed three times
because uh just as many other questions
that have come up in the meantime um
so some context here
Chris you've you've kind of answered
this you mentioned dual as in d-u-a-l
and then Anna brought up like is there
some kind of competition to dual a
d-u-e-l going on and how do we put those
two things together and me always
thumping the table about minimum two we
have to have to keep at least
two truisms up at once if we're going to
gain some sense around things I want to
go back to that lock
loc C slide if we can for a second
because Chris you mentioned
your statement was you draw a boundary
and to me there's a lot of information
packed in those four words
um
you can draw and you can undraw you can
bound you can Unbound
those are perfectly contextless subject
matter
information carrying
frames but you also have in that packet
you and at which are
imperfect orientations an indefinite
article and all of us occupying a slide
here none of us claiming to be anything
other than a contradiction
so one
aspect of that packet two words of it
literally half of it is is perfectly
contextless
and is information carrying and the
other literally
half of that is
prediction matter or information
graphing it's literally the the
byproduct or the
the space-time construct that that is
included so I guess what I'm wondering
is is
how do we make these different matters
the subject matter and the prediction
matter Tango how do we get them to
relate because
in the session five
you went on a detour you said we'll take
a detour which is it holds this exact
same structure as you draw a boundary so
there's perfect information and there's
imperfect information in that they're
dancing we do this all the time this
seems to be at a minimum what
information theory is and that's why I
want to kind of go back to this slide
because this slide was in a much earlier
session
but it got to session five where the
context could be
recapitulated and so I'm wondering
whether or not
we can really talk about
Quantum information without the
classical or if if there's if that's
even possible
um well uh I'll go back to Boris Bohr's
statement in his night 2028 paper uh he
basically said the answer to that
question is no
uh that uh we're humans we have to
communicate with each other we have to
do it in language
and that's classical communication
and if
sorry while we are doing that while
while we're having this conversation
we can't be worried about
the question of do I still exist
or you know do you still exist
we can worry about that question but we
can't do it at the same time that we're
having this conversation about
of the theory of lot protocols or or
exchanging data from a bell epr
experiment
and that's of course deeply paradoxical
and I think that's just the situation
we're in he said none of us are claiming
to be anything other than a
contradiction uh it's it's a good thing
that we
are
self-conscious about the fact that we're
we're doing something contradictory here
or potentially contradictory here
a a colleague and I wrote a paper
several years ago
uh called science generates limit
paradoxes
and we
basically
uh
rehearsed a version of this very
discussion that we're having right now
and the the upshot of that paper is that
in any situation in which
a science can
turn its theoretical apparatus
onto its own practice
so
for example when physics can
uh turn this analysis of of
boundaries onto the practice of physics
then it generates paradoxes
and those paradoxes have a particular
structure
which is the structure that a priest I
can't remember his first name
a logician who works in non uh
of dialectic logic calls the limit
paradox
and
it you know all of this is coupled to
girdles theoremen and these other
paradoxes of self-reference or or
aspects of self-reference
but I think this I think this situation
really is ubiquitous and inescapable
that
uh
as soon as we applied the tools of
science to the practice of science
we generate these paradoxical situations
in which
we have to acknowledge that we are
entities of a certain sort
and
that
we are
constructing
our theories
using a
faculty of imagination
that lets us act as if we don't have a
point of view
uh so it lets us act as if what we're
talking about is point of view
independent
but our our theories themselves tell us
that we have points of view and that
they're important
so we're stuck in this paradoxical
situation I I don't know whether that's
what you're trying to point to here but
it's
what
um I immediately leap to
hearing what you said
yeah a lot there anyone else want to add
a peace
now I'm going to have to go away so
thank you Chris we'll stay for a few
minutes thank you though this was
awesome we're really looking forward to
lecture six
okay thank you all and thank you all for
attending this discussion session it's
it's nice to have this kind of
uh
real-time discussion which is missing
during the actual lecture sessions so I
appreciate it thanks again see you thank
you thank you Chris
ciao
Kate do you want to ask anything or
anyone can can just bring up anything
they're thinking right now
nothing in
really looking for looking forward to
the last lecture
on the biology of it all
great
well any other thoughts or questions or
if anyone in the live chat has a thought
or a question they can write it and
we'll read it in the coming minutes
but I just wanted to thank you for
creating the space
um it's been absolutely
amazing that I even that I was able to
find this
um
situation where people are talking about
enormous questions
a very difficult questions and
um
and I I just want I just thought I'd
share that I
um find in Academia
there's
I don't know why we're not having these
conversations and I've been
um it's been like a 10-year Journey
and I have finally found this group I
just wanted to express my
gratitude
thank you
I'll read a question from the live chat
and anyone can give their thoughts
so Mills 8102 wrote
it seems that consilience would aim to
ameliorate the problems of
self-reference is this a category of
solution that seems valuable or fraught
could consilience ameliorate the
problems of self-reference
yes Dean
can I just ask a different question
built on that which is
what if the contradiction is a feature
as opposed to a fraughtness
do I contradict myself very well then I
contain multitudes there's the Whitman
angle then there's the William Blake
life is a fiction and is made up of
contradiction
so what is the problem of self-reference
whose problem is it Harris
yeah I will try to answer a bit
on both questions and by offering my
my views from the cognitive science
perspective
basically I think it has to do with
consilience has to do with the numerous
cognitive bias that we all we all are
let's say as uh subjected to so there is
a very long list of cognitive biases and
there are more than 100 listed I think
so uh
this is one of the challenges in terms
of achieving let's say a good levels of
conciliency
across various domains
so this is what I wanted to add
another thought on that is consilience
though it can mean many things uh
synthesis
oh yeah please honor go ahead oh yeah I
just so I
don't really have
insights into
the self-referencing problem I need to
do a lot of thinking about that
um but
coming from
training in evolutionary biology
and
spending you know graduate school
post-graduate school working on
explanations where
we
thought of many
hypotheses models
Etc
based on a goal which is organisms are
designed to maximize their Fitness
and of course her lots of we know that
there are lots of problems with that
and it turns out with our data what we
found is that was not the case
uh in our in the populations that we're
working with too often the goal did not
seem to be Fitness
um
so but what God experienced KB is that
there was something we could hang on to
in order to
uh allow ourselves to propose models for
why humans behave the way they do and
the decisions that they make
um so that's why I go back to goals
because
if if at whatever level of collective
intelligence we're talking about there
is a goal
but even in
Harris please let me know if I'm this
will be correct that even cognitive
biases exists
they exist because there is some goal
and therefore we can talk about
cognitive biases with respect to some
goal
yes there is some sort of teleonomy in
conscious agents or cultural systems as
I call them
and it has to do with with course yes
and
cognitive biases and and the limitations
on the knowledge let's say maybe it's
limitations on parts of the knowledge
representation on that each of us has
and maybe there are limitations in terms
of access to to knowing and there are
various forms of knowing so it depends
it depends on many things and
for example one of the
cognitive buyers that I believe can have
a negative impact on on conciliency
let's say in in addressing the this
self-referentiality
will be the halo effect
so where you seem to
[Music]
prioritize let's say or give some
advantage to some types of individuals
ideas or even
theories
because of that hello or whatever reason
that is paid it is based on maybe on
many different things maybe on your past
history or other things so
thank you Anna and um if I may add
something uh rather briefly um your
question reminded me of um Levins um and
I think it was written with Phil uh
their proposal about the reduction of
stress as a goal that con that guy is
the emergence of collective structures
is one of the papers uh formulated that
um that that seems to be
the goal that drives things as they grow
in complexity reduction of collective
stress or reduction of stress at any
level
yeah I don't remember the title of the
paper but that was them just to identify
understood it correctly
thank you I'll look that up great
another piece that of the Levinson
Fields collaboration that Chris alluded
to earlier is that the notion of
computation is Observer dependent that's
poly computation if there was a fully
encrypted computation
an observer without the key would only
be seeing noise to them whereas if they
were to have the decryption key then
they could fully understand and go into
more detail about the computation so
then
let's say that we're in relation or
observing or investigating some life
phenomena at some scale but we're
speaking the scale free setting but
we're observing a thing that's there
people have ascribed different goals
to describe
what we call goal-oriented Behavior like
seemingly to survive or assumingly to
have evolutionary Fitness
however
one
an observer could also project different
proximate goals like the goal to
minimize stress the goal to minimize
free energy the goal to minimize
surprise
those proximate Observer proposed goals
as if goals
may be exactly isomorphic or aligned
with Fitness maximization
so that could just be multiple
perspectives of projective goals and
whatever the Observer projects
that doesn't mean it describes the the
actual
process of the phenomena at all there's
just nothing Alice can make any story
about Bob and it it may or may not have
anything to do or even be possible to be
of the kind that Bob tells about himself
Dean
necessary I want to just piggyback on
that Daniel this is really huge and
important the moment you use the word
goals or the moment you use the word
Fitness you are assuming context
whereas a lot of this stuff that's
happening on this holographic screen is
completely abstractless abstracted and
completely context less
there's no no context required
so if you're going to focus on that part
of it as long as you can juggle both at
the same time and keep the two things
apart because one does not require
context the other completely assumes
that context is given and now you're
taking that into your Calculus right but
they're not the same thing so I'm just I
want to reinforce what Daniel just said
thank you Dean Ian
then continue
thank you yeah I was just
maybe reinforcing what you were saying
or
reflecting on it I was thinking about
the behaviors we see
in other animals and even ourselves that
we might not think are related to
Fitness
like I don't know there's those kind of
um gazelle type creatures that just jump
into the air and like but they seem to
do that at a time which might make them
be
um predated upon by a some tiger or lion
which
you know it's you have to then all the
sort of
I'll just try and figure out how is this
related to Fitness
um we may do the same you know if I go
and mow my lawn
waste half a Sunday afternoon mowing my
lawn what's that got to do with my
fitness well actually it's to do with
keeping up with the Joneses and um my
social status so
um it's really hard to actually know
what my behavior is about I can create a
story to say that it's to do with uh
minimizing free energy or Fitness but
really is it or not I don't know is that
kind of what you were
getting out or something different
yeah that's great playing also it's it's
come up several times about goals
the term goal is not to be found within
the active inference ontology strictly
speaking that's why we have so much fun
with what we expect and what we prefer
how can it be what we expect and be the
positive thing that we pursue well
that's how Paths of least action work
and then if somebody else wants to look
at that path of least action and say
well here was a mile point and this is
where it looked like they were heading
north and this is where it looked like
the goal was to evade this those are all
stories that an observer could tell
about a path or that the path might tell
itself about its own path but those goal
narratives
don't need to be implemented proximally
or primally with goals as a kind of
core player in the active inference
ontology
I'll read some of these great comments
and questions just if anybody has a
thought on them from the live chat
just feel free
John Reed wrote
what does the active inference group I
think that's us
but includes everyone
think about the equation of pilot wave
with many worlds recently expounded upon
by Chris O'Dowd at PBS I found it to be
mixing terms and frustrating personally
any thoughts on pilot wave and many
worlds
and or I would also just be curious on
like the physics or technical side
where does what Chris is sharing connect
to these kinds of discussions that
people have about
many worlds
and different interpretations of quantum
uh yeah that's a great question so I I
don't know that I can answer it
um
I know that uh when it comes to
interpretations of quantum mechanics
whether you know the collapse or the
many worlds or whatever
I I think what they're hinting at is is
an increase would probably answer
something along those lines that
quantum theory is fundamentally about
information and until until we make
sense of that
um fully and and and fully
spell out all the details
I think this philosophical issues are
the interpretations of quantum mechanics
are going to linger I am I don't have
any strong thoughts
uh on interpretations and I would
I would say I'm a an agnostic about
about interpretations of quantum
mechanics I I don't I don't know that
I'll subscribe to any of them
I don't have the slightest uh idea about
it
cool hairs
regarding pilot wave I was
conversing with chat GPT and I actually
asked what did uh thought about a pilot
wave after watching
a lecture on it and then I got in
tricked and I wanted to ask and this
actually happened the the model started
replying and I got the chance to read a
bit the the reply and the reply was like
it is very interesting but most probably
is not wrong is not correct it is wrong
and then it must have reached some sort
of information goal it retracted the the
reply and is replied to me can you ask
me a different question
so this is what uh this is my short
experience with pilot wave theory yeah
ask a question is a pilot wave more or
less than 100 feet in height
so yes exactly exactly 100
um
any other thoughts or questions
it's a fun and Lively live chat too
which is always
fun
yeah well we are um
coming right along in the year and now 5
6 completed
with
this course
so
any comments that anyone here just wants
to make in a closing route anybody who
who wants to can go for it
um yeah I have a question if if
questions come up
have come up during the session
yes when could I who could I send them
to and how
great question
in the video description
you can get to the syllabus of the
course and one of the pages on the
course website course syllabus is a
question and answer form so you'll see
several dozen questions that people have
already written and Chris gives answers
and then it's publicly posted all of the
lectures discussions and questions and
answers will be published after the
course
so every question no matter from where
or where to
all of these questions are encouraged it
only makes it a richer and more
relevance publication
thank you
okay Ian Harris or Dean
yes Susan also says post and Discord
great point
yeah I just wanted to add a small Point
as a conclusion from my personal
personal perspective I really find that
the ideas or the ideas of Chris fields
they can be revolutionized a
revolutionary let's say in in a variety
of and different
fields fields and I can see it in in
Quantum cryptography
and also about the what I've mentioned
before in terms of quantum knowledge
representation
so these are the two fields that I can
clearly exceed so it is great to be able
to
participate in this conversation so once
again thanks to everyone
great to participate in this
conversation or Quantum knowledge
representation whichever you prefer
enter
any last comments
uh not really just looking forward to
the next one I guess
next year this is going to be an ongoing
thing
yes
we'll come back stronger next year for
sure
okay
what a ride thank you all see you next
time
bye
bye everyone